Whiting, Indiana: Generational Memory 1991-1993 ohrc102
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
- Gresko, Joseph, May 14, 1991; 91-023; Bodnar, John; 38 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 74 minutes; index
  Joseph Gresko, born on February 14, 1921, recalls his family and childhood in Whiting, Indiana, and tells of his work experiences at Standard Oil Company and of his experiences during World War II. He comments on the centrality of religion to Whiting community life, where every parish had a baseball team in the nineteen twenties and nineteen thirties. In addition, Mr. Gresko remembers Prohibition and the bootlegging that occurred. He also discusses the layoffs caused by machinery modernization and technological innovation at Standard Oil, the pensions Standard Oil provided, and his own involvement in local politics.
  bootlegging; ethnic diversity; hoboes; industrial modernization; local politics; Pearl Harbor; pensions; petroleum coke; pollution; Prohibition; unions; World War II; American Legion; Standard Oil Company; Bessignano, Nick; Kocan, Helen; Schrage, Waller
- Gresko, Sophie, March 12, 1991; October 11, 1991; 91-022; Bodnar, John; 55 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 106 minutes; index
  Sophie Gresko, born in 1902 in Czechoslovakia, recalls her journey to the United States in 1911, her childhood, family, and her adult life in Whiting, Indiana, and her employment history as a young widow with two children to support. She describes the creation of a Slovak bank in Whiting, community life in the town, and the norm among Slovak women of using midwives rather than doctors in giving birth in the first few decades of the twentieth century.
  Czechoslovakia; community life; Education; emigration; midwifery; Slovak Dom; First Catholic Slovak Ladies Association; Liberty Savings and Loan Association; Whiting Community Center; Ciesar, John; Kocan, Helen; Kozacik, Michael
- Haynes, Charlotte, December 6, 1990; 91-011; Klemm, Verda; 29 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 80 minutes; index
  Charlotte Haynes, born on August 16, 1940, discusses her family and upbringing in rural Kentucky, the move to Whiting, Indiana, and her career as a librarian. She speaks of her education, the Civil Rights Movement, her memories of the atomic bombs being dropped on Nagasaki and Hiroshima, and of the Vietnam War. She comments on the negative impact her father's alcoholism has on her family and the importance of the Southern Baptist Church to her youth. In addition, she briefly discusses the best and worst United States presidents, in her opinion, and her hobbies of gardening and camping.
  librarian; camping; child discipline; Civil Rights Movement; Education; gardening; Southern Baptist Church; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; Whiting Library; Johnson, Lyndon Baines; Truman, Harry S.; Reagan, Ronald Wilson; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962
- Herakovich, Elizabeth, May 30, 1991; 91-135; Dabertin, David; 19 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 47 minutes; index
  Elizabeth Herakovich, born on August 3, 1929, joined by her husband, Robert Herakovich, discusses how and when she and her husband met, her experiences during World War II, including having five brothers in the service, and her children. She recalls attending the 1964 New York World's Fair and traveling with her husband and children, and she shares her opinions on the Vietnam War, pollution, and local crime. In addition, Mrs. Herakovich comments on her education and employment history.
  New York, New York; 1955 Standard Oil fire; 1964 New York World's Fair; local crime; pollution; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; Standard Oil Company; State Bank of Whiting
- Herakovich, Robert, May 30, 1991; 91-048; Dabertin, David; 34 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 64 minutes; index
  Robert Herakovich, born on December 20, 1919, recalls his family and childhood in Whiting, Indiana, and describes the physical changes that the environment and real estate of Whiting have undergone. He discusses his work in and the importance of the steel mills, Standard Oil Company, and AMOCO to Whiting. In addition, Mr. Herakovich speaks of his service in World War II, and his memories of the 1955 Standard Oil fire.
  Gary, Indiana; India; Whiting, Indiana; 1955 Standard Oil fire; family values; steel mills; unions; World War II; AMOCO; Standard Oil Company
- Hiduke, Carolyn; Hiduke, Andrew, March 3, 1992; 91-154; Bodnar, John; 60 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 106 minutes; index
  Carolyn and Andrew Hiduke speak of their respective youths and families in Whiting, Indiana, the family values with which they were reared and which they later adopted, and employment in Whiting. The Hidukes discuss the grocery store they owned, Mr. Hiduke's career as a probation officer in the juvenile courts, and their move to Arizona for retirement. In addition, they comment on their opinion that society is breaking down and that American culture has become increasingly materialistic.
  probation officer; Arizona; Hessville, Indiana; 1929 stock market crash; child discipline; community life; juvenile court; materialism; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; St. John's Elementary School; Union Tank Car Company; Cunningham, Wayne; Truman, Harry S.
- Hlebasko, Mary; Hlebasko, George, November 8, 1990; 91-005; Bodnar, John; 58 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 99 minutes; index
  George Hlebasko, born in 1907, and his wife, Mary Hlebasko, born in 1910, each recall their family's history of emigration to America from Czechoslovakia, their childhoods in Whiting, Indiana, and their education at Catholic schools. The speak of local businesses, the importance and role of Standard Oil in their lives, local politics, and community life in Whiting. In addition, the Hlebaskos discuss the many houses they have built over the years and the change in associated costs, as well as the disintegration of modern society represented by increased divorce rates and the lack of child discipline.
  child discipline; class segregation; community life; Czechoslovakian immigrants; divorce; Fourth of July; Great Depression; local crime; local politics; pollution; still cleaning; Congress of Industrial Organizations; Kolar's Saloon; St. John's Elementary School; St. Mary's Byzantine Church; Standard Oil Comapny; Hlebasko; Suranich
- Hodges, Wade; Hodges, Jimmie, May 15, 1991; 91-033; Berry, Chad; 39 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 69 minutes; index
  Wade Hodges, born on December 13, 1949, and his wife, Jimmie Hodges, born on October 12, 1950, each recall their childhoods and families in Arkansas, their move to Whiting, Indiana, and they discuss their children, Jason and Travis, who are present for part of the interview. The Hodges relate their respective employment histories, and Mr. Hodges emphasizes the benefits of working at AMOCO and being a member of the labor union there. In addition, the Hodges speak of their family values and views on and experiences with child discipline.
  Arkansas; child discipline; family values; unions; AMOCO; Standard Oil Company
- Homco, Edward C., November 9, 1990; 91-008; Bodnar, John; 27 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  Father Edward C. Homco, born in 1919, discusses his family, childhood, and the tight-knit Slovak community in Whiting, Indiana. He speaks of the recent trends of materialism and individualism as contributing to the breakdown of society. In addition, Father Homco comments on the Catholic priesthood, experiences in different parishes and with fellow priests, and on his memories of Prohibition and Whiting's Fourth of July parade.
  Catholic priest; Czechoslovakia; Whiting, Indiana; Americanization; community life; Fourth of July; materialism; Prohibition; Slovak Dom; AMOCO; Immaculate Conception Catholic Church; Society of the Precious Blood; St. John's Catholic Church
- Hovanec, Florence, August 18, 1992; 91-167; Orr, Lisa; 32 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes; index
  Florence Hovanec, born on September 18, 1918, recalls her parents and childhood in Whiting, Indiana, the life she made there raising her own family, and community life in general. She discusses her memories of the Great Depression, the changes in family values that she has observed over the years, and the increasing diversity of Whiting's population. In addition, Mrs. Hovanec speaks of the importance of Catholicism and her church in her life.
  Catholicism; community life; ethnic diversity; family values; Great Depression; immigration quotas; St. John the Baptist Church
- Jancosek, George, January 28, 1991; 91-017; Dabertin, David; 24 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 85 minutes; index
  George Jancosek, a dentist and orthodontist born on September 5, 1932, recalls his family and childhood in Whiting, Indiana, growing up with no central heating or hot water, and the work ethic and emphasis on education he gained from his Czechoslovakian parents. He speaks of local politics, the importance of Catholicism, the strong cultural ties in the community, and the setting up of his dental practice in Whiting. In addition, Mr. Jancosek cites America's moral degradation and increased materialism as some of the major changes that have occurred over the years.
  dentist; orthodontist; Austria-Hungary; Gary, Indiana; Korea; Catholicism; dental practice; Education; local politics; morals; pollution; Slovak immigrants; steel mills; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; Standard Oil Company; United States Army; Bercik; Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
- Jancosek, JoAnn, January 29, 1991; 91-016; Dabertin, David; 22 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 57 minutes; index
  JoAnn Jancosek, born on February 23, 1940, recalls her youth and family in Whiting, Indiana, where her father was a police officer and she had to take over many of the household duties because her ailing mother was unable to perform them. One of her earliest memories is of the Standard Oil fire in 1955. She describes local politics, her participation in Polish folk dancing and her vague memories of World War II. In addition, she speaks of her college education and life in Robertsdale, Indiana.
  Robertsdale, Indiana; 1955 Standard Oil fire; garbage burning; local politics; Polish folk dancing; pollution; World War II; AMOCO; St. Adalbert's Catholic Church; University of Detroit Mercy
- Jancosek, John, February 9, 1991; 91-014; Dabertin, David; 40 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 111 minutes; index
  John Jancosek, born on December 24, 1919, recalls his childhood and family in Whiting, Indiana, experiences in the United States Navy, and his wife and marriage. He remembers the Great Depression and how it brought family values and a very strong work ethic to the forefront, both within his family and in the community of Whiting. Mr. Jancosek discusses the discrimination Slavs were often subjected to, his memories of the 1955 Standard Oil fire, the negative aspects of labor unions, and the pollution that has characterized Whiting and its environs. In addition, he speaks of his United States Navy service prior to and during World War II, and also during the Korean War.
  China; Japan; 1955 Standard Oil fire; community life; discrimination; Education; ethnic diversity; Great Depression; home remedies; pollution; unions; work ethic; World War II; Standard Oil Company; United States. Navy
- Judson, James, November 13, 1991; 91-146; Klemm, Verda; 23 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 43 minutes; index
  James Judson, born on April 21, 1916, recalls his family and life in Whiting, Indiana, including his experiences traveling and performing with Father Lach's band in the United States and in Europe. He discusses his views on women working outside of the home and relates his memories of being in the United States Coast Guard during World War II. In addition, Mr. Judson speaks of working in New Jersey and his work as a chemist.
  chemist; New Jersey; national economy; women workers; World War II; Standard Oil Company; United States Coast Guard
- Jurbala, Anne M., August 19, 1992; 91-169; Orr, Lisa; 25 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 54 minutes; index
  Anne M. Jurbala, born in 1924, recalls her family and youth in Whiting, Indiana, how she met her husband and their life together, and the tight-knit Slovak community of which she was a part. She remembers the effects of World War II on her life, and, prior to that, the financial struggles she and her family experienced during the Great Depression. A devout Catholic, Mrs. Jurbala speaks of the importance of prayer and the centrality of religion to her life.
  Czechoslovakia; Gary, Indiana; Catholicism; community life; Great Depression; national politics; pollution; women workers; World War II; AMOCO; Dance Land
- Kaminsky, Ann Marie, May 14, 1991; 91-026; Bodnar, John; 38 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 98 minutes; index
  Ann Marie Kaminsky, born on November 17, 1914, recalls her family, childhood, marriage, and life in Whiting, Indiana in this interview. She discusses community life, the work ethic of her parents and of her own generation, and she shares her memories of the 1955 Standard Oil fire.
  1955 Standard Oil fire; work ethic; Standard Oil Company
- Kasper, Jim; Kasper, Beth, July 27, 1991; 91-040; Orr, Lisa; 56 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 96 minutes; index
  Jim and Beth Kasper, born on June 19, 1964 and December 21, 1963, respectively, discuss each of their parents, families, and childhoods in Whiting, Indiana. They speak of the development of their relationship, the values they share, and the role of Catholicism in their lives. In addition, they comment on the moral disintegration of the country, the national economy, and on national politics.
  Catholicism; college education; family values; national economy; national politics; personal finances; real estate; Republican Party
- Kirk, Leonard; Kirk, Lucille, July 20, 1991; 91-035; Orr, Lisa; 33 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 80 minutes; index; poem by interviewee
  Leonard Kirk, born on September 6, 1924, and his wife, Lucille Kirk, born on August 13, 1926, each recall their childhoods and families, and they discuss their relationship and the life they made for themselves in Whiting, Indiana. The Kirks speak of community life and retirement in Whiting, their memories of the Great Depression and World War II, their values, and of the shift in values toward materialism that characterizes modern America.
  community life; family values; farming; Great Depression; retirement; unions; World War II
- Klemm, Barry, December 18, 1992; 91-173; Wolford, John; 71 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 171 minutes; index; 4 photographs of interviewee
  Barry Klemm, born in April of 1947, recalls his youth in Whiting, Indiana, and extensively discusses each of his parents and his grandparents, and his relationship with each of them. He also thoroughly describes his employment history and career, which began in the steel mills and expanded to construction, real estate, and finally, the professional business world. Mr. Klemm retains especially strong memories of the assassination of President Kennedy and the Standard Oil fire of 1955. In addition, he speaks of his values, especially of the value his father placed on self-sufficiency and of his contact with, participation in, and opinions of labor unions.
  real estate agent; Indianapolis, Indiana; Lafayette, Indiana; Paducah, Kentucky; 1955 Standard Oil fire; Cold War; community life; family values; John F. Kennedy assassination; pollution; unions; women workers; Condes' Restaurant; Inland Steel; Whiting Community Center; Youngstown Sheet and Tube; McTague; McTague, Jerome "Mick"; Plewniak, Ron
- Koch, Albert R., February 19, 1991; 91-020; Klemm, Verda; 39 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 100 minutes; index; photo of interviewee, articles by interviewee
  Albert R. Koch, born on January 21, 1941, shares his memories of his youth, parents, and family in Whiting, Indiana, expressing his love for the area and for his parents and the values they taught him. Mr. Koch speaks of his education at Whiting High School, his work at Inland Steel, and his college education at Indiana State University. He describes community life in Whiting, the impact of Catholicism on his life, and he discusses his philosophy of life.
  author; industrial technology teacher; librarian; Catholicism; community life; Education; family values; Radio; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; work ethic; World War II; Indiana State University; Inland Steel; Standard Oil Company; Thorton Fractional North; Whiting High School; Neville, Mark; Truman, Harry S.; Yanas, Andy
- Kompier, Alexander, April 6, 1991; 91-140; Del Negro, Giovanna; 51 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 120 minutes; index
  Alexander Kompier, born in November of 1916, recalls his family and youth in Whiting, Indiana, sharing his memories of Prohibition and the Great Depression. He speaks of his service in World War II and how his time spent in an infantry unit in Sicily, Algiers, and England, among other places, stimulated a lifelong love of world travel. After his discharge, he returned and completed his undergraduate and master's degrees with the help of the GI Bill. In addition, Mr. Kompier discusses community life in Whiting, the building of a new marina there, its ethnic diversity, and the high quality of its schools.
  high school teacher; Algiers; Bloomington, Indiana; Sicily; Soviet Union; Education; ethnic diversity; Great Depression; Prohibition; Whiting marina; world travel; World War II; George Rogers Clark High School; Indiana University; Northwestern University; Salvation Army; Standard Oil Company; Whiting Community Center; Whiting High School; Homman, Florence
- Kosalko, Gayle, July 23, 1991; 91-039; Klemm, Verda; 27 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 63 minutes; index
  Gayle Kosalko, born on March 30, 1949, discusses her family history and home life growing up in Whiting, Indiana, as well as her own husband and children and their life in Whiting. She speaks of her college education, her political affiliation and Republican beliefs, teaching, and her memories of the Vietnam War and John F. Kennedy assassination. In addition, she describes her involvement in local community youth musical theater productions.
  community theater; Education; family values; John F. Kennedy assassination; national politics; teaching; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; women workers; World War II; Park College; Pennsylvania Avenue Players
- Kovach, John, July 23, 1991; 91-038; Orr, Lisa; 25 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 52 minutes; index
  John Kovach describes the many differences between the lives of his parents, Czechoslovakian immigrants, in Whiting, Indiana, and his own life in Whiting. He discusses his employment at Standard Oil Company, pollution and local politics, his memories of the Great Depression, and briefly highlights his experiences serving in the infantry during World War II. In addition, he shares his opinion on the best and worst United States presidents.
  community life; ethnic diversity; Great Depression; local politics; pollution; steel mills; unions; women workers; World War II; Dance Land; Standard Oil Company
- Kraly, Rosemary M., January 22, 1992; 91-156; Dabertin, David; 28 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes; index
  Born on May 28, 1926, Rosemary M. Kraly discusses her memories of the private bootlegging that occurred in Whiting, Indiana, during Prohibition, and she speaks of how she met and married her husband. A longtime homemaker, she comments on local employment, her education at Clark High School, and the expectation that she would work immediately after high school until she was married. In addition, Mrs. Kraly recalls the 1955 Standard Oil fire.
  homemaker; Streator, Illinois; 1955 Standard Oil fire; gambling; pollution; Prohibition; Whiting MacNamara basketball team; Clark High School; Standard Oil Company
- Kus, Leo J.; Michalak, Frank, March 8, 1991; 91-024; Craver, Amy; 45 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 131 minutes; index
  Leo J. Kus, born on June 7, 1919, and Frank Michalak, born on December 8, 1917, recall their childhoods and coming of age in Whiting, Indiana. They speak of their experiences during the Great Depression and World War II, their employment at Standard Oil Company, and their experiences with labor unions. They discuss Whiting's community life and the changes it has undergone over the years. Mr. Kus cites the main problem of America as the replacement of faith in God by unfounded faith in man.
  construction pipe fitter; Poland; Catholicism; community life; ethnic diversity; family values; Great Depression; local industry; local politics; Religion; unions; women workers; work ethic; World War II; Dance Land; Democratic Party; Standard Oil Company; Whiting Community Center; Miller, R.B.; Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
- Kus, Leo J., October 11, 1991; 91-143; Bodnar, John; 23 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  Leo J. Kus, born on June 7, 1919, describes the importance of Standard Oil Company to the town of Whiting, Indiana, his years of employment there, the benefits, the union, and the work ethic associated with his years there. He discusses his family, the effects of the Great Depression on local employment, and the high value he placed on education for his own children.
  construction pipe fitter; 1955 Standard Oil fire; employee benefits; family values; Great Depression; labor strikes; layoffs; unions; work ethic; Standard Oil Company; Swearingen, John
- Labda, Mildred, November 8, 1990; 91-006; Bodnar, John; 46 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 75 minutes; index
  Mildred Labda, born in 1903, recalls her childhood, her emigration to America from Czechoslovakia, and her youth and life in Whiting, Indiana. She extensively discusses her family, husband, and children, including their employment and participation in World War II. Mrs. Labda speaks of community life, the Slovak Lutheran Church, and national politics in this interview, as well as emphasizing the importance of religion and a strong work ethic in her life.
  Czechoslovakia; emigration; Great Depression; national politics; Religion; Slovak Dom; Slovak Lutheran Church; work ethic; Haluska, George; Labda, Gerald; Labda, Godfrey; Labda, Lodie; McKinley, Martha Labda
- Labus, Paul, May 4, 1993; 91-175; Dabertin, David; 22 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 54 minutes; index
  Paul Labus, born on October 24, 1955, describes his youth and family growing up in Whiting and Hammond, Indiana. He discusses his career as a painter, his limited employment history, the strong work ethic of his father, and the impact of the Vietnam War on his generation. In addition, Mr. Labus remembers the enjoyment he experienced during Whiting's annual Fourth of July parade and carnival.
  painter; Hammond, Indiana; Fourth of July; pollution; racism; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; work ethic; Humes and Berg
- Labus, Stanley, April 6, 1991; 91-139; Del Negro, Giovanna; 47 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 76 minutes; index
  Stanley Labus, born on November 6, 1926, discusses his Polish parents and their emigration to America early in the twentieth century and recalls his family and childhood in Whiting, Indiana. He speaks of his service in the United States Navy during World War II. In addition, he comments on the values transmitted to him by his parents, the role of Catholicism in his life, his employment at AMOCO, and the activities of the Ku Klux Klan in Whiting in the past.
  East Moline, Illinois; Poland; 1933 National Industrial Recovery Act; Catholicism; community life; Education; emigration; family values; Great Depression; local employment; local politics; steel mills; unions; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; AMOCO; Keyes Fibre Corporation; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ); Standard Oil Company; Clark, George Rogers; McKenna, Joseph; Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
- Marcisz, John J., March 3, 1992; 91-152; Bodnar, John; 65 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 129 minutes; index